<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter written by a Iesuite to the Queens Majestie, March, XXII. Wherein he useth divers subtle insinuations to Her Majesty, for the Kings Majesties repealing and recalling of the lawes and proclamations against the Iesuits, priests, and recusants. With a brief consideration of the reasons, intimated in the letter, and a just confutation of them.</title>
            <author>M. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C84</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E141_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16022</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859955</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156556</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156556)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 25:E141[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter written by a Iesuite to the Queens Majestie, March, XXII. Wherein he useth divers subtle insinuations to Her Majesty, for the Kings Majesties repealing and recalling of the lawes and proclamations against the Iesuits, priests, and recusants. With a brief consideration of the reasons, intimated in the letter, and a just confutation of them.</title>
                  <author>M. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Watkins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on A3v: M.C.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>In the imprint, the "t" in "printed" is inverted.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156556:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 117 -->
            <p>A LETTER <hi>WRITTEN BY A</hi> IESVITE <hi>TO THE</hi> QVEENS MAJESTIE, <hi>MARCH, XXII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN He uſeth divers ſubtle inſinuations to Her Majeſty, for the Kings Majeſties repealing and recalling of the Lawes and Proclamations againſt the Ieſuits, Prieſts, and Recuſants.</p>
            <p>With a brief conſideration of the Reaſons, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in the Letter, and a juſt Confutation of them.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>Iohn Watkins.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:156556:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 118 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:156556:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 118 -->
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> JESUITES LETTER TO the Queens Maieſtie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt mighty Princeſſe;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT hath alwais bin accounted honourable, for great perſonages to have pitty and compaſſion of afflicted and diſtreſſed ſouls; but eſpecially if they were guiltleſſe and innocent, and ſuffered for good, yea for Gods cauſe.</p>
            <p>A moſt fit occaſion of exerciſing this heroicall act is now offered to your Majeſty, by the manifold moleſtations infliſted upon <hi>Engliſh Catholiques,</hi> the truth of whoſe religion and innocency is brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced in our many Treatiſes; for which cauſe I have thought it no preſumption, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to your Royall Protection.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of <hi>Heſter</hi> is not unknown to your Majeſty, and wee doubt her example deſerveth no leſſe imitation then admiration, by her mediation with King <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> the Nation of the Iews was delivered from an univerſall overthrow; and why ſhould not Queen <hi>Marie</hi> prevail as far with King <hi>Charles,</hi> for ancient and Chriſtian <hi>Catholiques.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156556:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 119 -->
            <p>Can any doubt, but that he would extend the Golden Rod of Clemency towards the deareſt Spouſe; yea rather divide his Kingdome then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny her requeſt: his Majeſty is already informed of former ſervices performed by <hi>Catholiques</hi> both to his Grandmother of happy memory, and himſelf, for which they crave no other recompence: or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but the recalling and repelling of ſuch <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations</hi> and Laws, as their Adverſaries have procured againſt them.</p>
            <p>This did Queen, <hi>Eſter</hi> obtain of King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> for the Jews. Thus wee Catholiques beſeech your Majeſty to motion for us; but yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that earneſtneſſe, which good <hi>Mordicheus</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, who ſpared not to tell the Queen, making ſome difficulty? That though ſhe held her peace, the Iewes ſhould be delivered by ſome other meanes, but that ſhe and her Fathers houſe ſhould periſh; onely wee will urge that which immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, who knoweth whether this was the cauſe of your Majeſties comming to the Crown, that you might be prepared againſt ſuch a time.</p>
            <p>This alſo we add, which makes the matter more eaſie: we deſire no mans harm but our own good, we wiſh for no mans fall that we may riſe: wee would rejoyce, but would have none to ſorrow: when our Country was ſeperated from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Faith, and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> all was done by great force and violence, wee hope when we ſhall return, all will bee compaſſed with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb facs="tcp:156556:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 119 -->courſe: and we would willingly admit that Expoſition, which one hath made of St. <hi>Edwards</hi> Viſion; if it had no other difficulty in it then this. Two Monks which this holy King had bin fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly acquainted with in <hi>NORMANDIE,</hi> and were now Saints in Heaven, appeared to him, and told him of his Countries, comming to a better e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, by propoſing unto him this Probleme; A green Tree being cut from the body, let it bee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated the ſpace of four Acres from the Root, which when mans hand compelling it, no neceſſity urging it, returning to the body, ſhall come again to the ancient Root, and taking ſap, ſhall flouriſh, and bear fruit again then, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By this green Tree, ſaith my Author, wee may very well underſtand the Kingdome of <hi>England:</hi> of which St. <hi>Edward,</hi> and thoſe holy <hi>Monks</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured the cutting it from the body, was dividing it from the Sea Apodilique, for the ſpace of four Acres, that is, for the time of four Princes Reigns, King <hi>Henrie,</hi> King <hi>Edward,</hi> Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherfore now what are we to expect, but that without all compulſion, or conſtraint, it ſhould return to the body and root again, and begin to flouriſh with Catholique Doctrine, and bear fruit of good works, by receiving the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p of Grace, which cannot bee out of the vertue of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, which conſiſteth of the foreſaid head and Members.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156556:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 120 -->
            <p>Thus he, and howſoever (as I ſaid) the reſt may be exproved, we ſhould like paſſing well this faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſweetneſſe without force and violence; and therfore doe earneſtly wiſh, that as the ſeperation between King <hi>Henry</hi> and Queen <hi>Katherine,</hi> was a great beginning of that other breach: ſo the inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable love of King <hi>Charles</hi> and Queen <hi>Marie</hi> might reſtore us to the ancient union, The very at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting of this Noble and Godly Enterpriſe, deſerveth immortall praiſes.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Henricus Roſas Carolus Regna.</hi> O that we might add, <hi>&amp; Maria Eccleſias.</hi>
               </salute>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt faithfull ſervant, and humble Orator, <hi>M. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="supporting_argument">
            <head>A brief conſideration of the Reaſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in the former Letter, for His Majeſties repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and recalling the Laws and Proclamations againſt Recuſants. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe firſt Reaſon, for the ſervices performed by the Catholiques to his Grand-mother.</p>
            <p>It is a conſiderable ſervice, for by the inſtigation and malice of the Jeſuits, and Romiſh Catholicks, were that Queen drawn and invited to thoſe tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous deſigns and practiſes againſt Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and the State; for which that great, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Princeſſe loſt her head.</p>
            <p>The 2. Reaſon, for the ſervices done to his Maj.
<pb facs="tcp:156556:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 120 -->this Jeſuite would not be ſeen to know, or at leaſt would not have it remembred, that deteſtable plot of the Powder Treaſon; wherby his Majeſties Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and His whole Progeny, and this State, had ſuffered in that execrable way, that no times could ever parallel.</p>
            <p>And for his Majeſties ſervice to himſelf in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, though this Letter might ſeem to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before this horrid Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> began; yet I cannot beleeve, but the ground-work &amp; plot therof was laid before this Letter: and alſo the diſcention between us and <hi>Scotland</hi> plotted: All which, who is ſo ignorant, as not to know that it proceeds from the Jeſuits and Romiſh Catholicks: Therfore let all out deſires to her Majeſty bee to move the King, that inſtead of <hi>Mordeca</hi>'s reward, they may have the juſt reward of trayterous <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> which they never yet failed to deſerve.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this alſo we add, which may make the matter more eaſie, we deſire no mans harm, but our good: we wiſh for no mans fall that we may riſe.</p>
            <p>This addition makes a fair gloſſe, but mark the conſequence, what followeth that State and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome wherin Idolatry is ſuffered to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? Whatſoever is offenſive unto God, is not to be tollerated; Idolatry it ſelf is offenſive unto God, and conſequently the exerciſe and permiſſion of the ſame. A Chriſtian Prince being the keeper of both tables of the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> ſhould not ſuffer I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry to defile the worſhip of God, within His Dominions.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever the good Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and other
<pb facs="tcp:156556:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 121 -->godly Princes are commended for in the Scripture, that Chriſtian Princes ought to imitate; therfore Chriſtian Princes ought to expell contrary wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, and to repreſſe Idolatry in like manner.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition is manifeſt, for whatſoever is written, is written for our inſtruction, the aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption is proved by induction. <hi>Aſa</hi> brake down the Altars and Images of ſtrange Gods, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> removed the high places and Groves, 2 <hi>Chron,</hi> 17.6: <hi>Ioſiah</hi> put down the <hi>Chemarines</hi> that were <hi>Idolatrous Prieſts, 2 Kings</hi> 23.5. <hi>Iacoh</hi> would not ſuffer Idolatry to be committed in his houſe, but buried all the Images under an Oak, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.5. All which were commended for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>We would rejoyce, but would have none to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row? What greater ſorrow can befall a State or Kingdome then the wrath of God to hang over their heads, which Idolatry and ſuperſtitious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip draws upon them where it is tolerated: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Almighty for a time permits, yet when his violl of wrath is ful wo be to that ſtate. Which let all of us humbly pray, may not fall upon this Nation, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
